创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness,
随着一声爆炸
and then, bang--
诞生了无尽膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在揭秘这个诡异
Every day new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
震撼 神秘莫测的
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
地方 - 我们所谓的《宇宙》
of a place we call "The Universe."
大量小行星撞击 从天降下死神
Enormous asteroid impacts that rain death from the sky,
行星对撞 把世界化为尘土
entire planets colliding and turning worlds into dust,
黑洞 上亿年间把星系的其他部分越驱越远
a black hole that's been blowing away the rest of its galaxy for 100 million years,
大质量恒星 震撼宇宙别无他求
and massive stars that rock the universe like nothing else.
准备灰飞烟灭在
Get ready to be blown away in a countdown
十大宇宙大爆发的倒数盘点中吧
of 10 of the largest explosions in the cosmos.
它们全都是宇宙间的爆炸之最
These are the biggest blasts in the universe.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：HDC字幕组 调校：晴天 招募Q号: 76846146
历史频道 - 宇宙 第4季第4集 爆炸之最
The History Channel - The Universe s04e04 Biggest Blasts
它们不仅能在弹指一挥间
They can not only wipe out cities
抹去我们数以百万计人口的城市
filled with millions of people in the blink of an eye,
而且还能毁灭整个大陆 行星
but can lay waste to entire continents, planets,
甚至撕裂星系
and even rip galaxies apart.
宇宙间到处都是剧烈的爆发
The universe is filled with tremendously violent explosions
爆炸和事件
and blasts and events.
祥和的地球生活
The calm serenity of life on Earth
一定程度上 是个例外 而不是常态
is, to some degree, the exception, not the norm.
它们不管是大规模碰撞还是整个恒星的爆发
And whether they're massive collisions or explosions of entire stars,
其要素大同小异
they all have important elements in common.
确实 换句话说 爆发或爆炸
Really, another way to say explosion or blast
就是能量的同时大释放
is just a big liberation of energy all at once.
你从已具结构的对象中释放大量的能量时
When you liberate a lot of energy in something that already has structure,
往往会破坏该结构 因此看上去极具破坏性
you tend to demolish the structure, so that seems very destructive,
但是自然规律会攫取能量
but the laws of nature will take energy
并将其改造成一些其它的形式
and reconstruct it into some other form.
1994年 苏梅克-列维九号彗星的20多块碎片
In 1994, more than 20 pieces of the Shoemaker-Levy 9 comet
痛击了木星
pummeled Jupiter.
大黑疤横跨木星表面
There were big black scars all across the face of Jupiter,
疤痕之大连业余望远镜都一目了然
so large even that they could be seen clearly even with amateur telescopes.
最大的彗星碎片超过了1英里宽
The largest comet fragment was more than a mile wide,
其冲击力相当于600万兆吨TNT
and the force of its impact was equal to 6 million megatons of TNT.
约是世界全部核武器的100倍还不止
That's about a hundred times or more of the entire nuclear arsenal of the world.
如果你在地球的每一个角落都放上一个炸弹
So if you took every bomb in every corner on Earth
同时爆炸成为一个大爆发
and exploded it in one big explosion,
都比不上这个碎片撞击木星所产生的能量
you wouldn't even begin to touch the power of this fragment colliding into Jupiter.
但是猜猜看 即使是此类能量都不够格
But guess what? Even that type of power isn't enough to qualify
成为宇宙间最大的爆炸之一
as one of the biggest blasts in the universe.
进入前10位的第一个项目具有N多倍的破坏性
The first event to make the top 10 was many times more devastating.
排名第10 - 死神从天而降
我们名录上最小的爆炸
The smallest blast on our list
可能还是大得足以抹去恐龙
may still have been big enough to wipe out the dinosaurs
因为其烟雾和碎片遮挡了阳光
by blocking out the Sun with smoke and debris.
那就是希克苏鲁伯撞击
It's the Chicxulub impact,
约6500万年前
the asteroid that crashed into Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula
小行星撞击墨西哥尤卡坦半岛
about 65 million years ago.
一块6英里宽的太空石头
A 6-mile-wide space rock,
大过珠峰
taller than Mount Everest and almost as wide,
闯入地球
thundered into Earth.
我现在坐在亚利桑那州流星陨石坑前面
So I'm sitting in front of Meteor Crater in Arizona,
它约四分之三英里宽
and this is about 3/4 of a mile wide.
如果我们开车跨越它
So if we were to drive across this
时速55到60迈 会要用上一分钟时间
at about 55 or 60 miles per hour, it would take, like, a minute.
撞击尤卡坦半岛的小行星所创造出来的弹坑
Well, the crater created by the asteroid that impacted the Yucatan Peninsula,
驱车以同样的速度跨越 需要两个多小时
it would take over two hours to drive it at about the same speed,
所以你可以想象那个弹坑比我身后的这个要大多少
so you can imagine how much larger that crater is than this one behind me.
直径112英里的弹坑大到足以放下纽约市
The 112-mile-diameter crater is big enough to fit New York City,
费城 以及两者之间的一切
Philadelphia, and everything in between inside.
假如撞击发生在今天 约有1200万人会当场毙命
If it struck today, about 12 million people would be killed instantly,
更不用提弹坑扩散所造成的破坏和伤亡
not to mention the damage and casualties that would spread beyond the crater.
那是因为每一个爆炸的能量释放有几个途径
That's because the energy in every blast is released in several ways,
例如撞击时的致盲闪光
such as light during the blinding flash of the impact,
热量 能够将野火蔓延至全球大部分地区
and heat, capable of spreading wildfires across much of the globe.
不过伴随撞击的 大部分破坏来自
But with collisions, most of the devastation comes
运动的能量 所谓的动能
from the energy of motion, known as kinetic energy,
产生弹坑 飞出碎片
which creates the crater and the flying debris.
创造希克苏鲁伯陨石坑的撞击所产生的能量
The energy in the impact that created the crater at Chicxulub
必定是十分巨大的 或许有2 5亿兆吨
had to have been enormous, probably about 250 million megatons.
那是巨大的能量
That's a lot of energy.
地球史上爆炸的最大炸弹是50兆吨
The largest bomb ever exploded on Earth was 50 megatons.
那对比2 5亿可以给你去判断
So that compared to 250 million gives you a sense.
也是击中木星的苏梅克-列维九号彗星
It was also about 40 times greater than the energy released
最大的碎片所释放能量的40倍
by the largest Shoemaker-Levy 9 comet fragment to hit Jupiter.
计算一颗庞大小行星撞击所释放的动能的过程中
In figuring out the kinetic energy released in a huge asteroid impact,
要命的是将某些非常庞大的数字
it's all a matter of plugging some very big numbers
插入一个简单的方程式
into a simple equation.
考虑这种碰撞的能量时
The key thing to keep in mind
要记住的关键之处
when considering the energy in these kinds of collisions
在于所谓的动能方程式
is that the formula for what's called the kinetic energy,
动能等于1/2 [M × V 的平方]
the energy of motion, is 1/2 [M x V squared],
质量乘以速度的平方
the mass and then the square of the velocities.
质量就是物体的重量
Mass is the weight of the object,
速度是其运动的速度
and velocity is the speed it's traveling.
巨大的能量可以来自
You can have a huge amount of energy
够重或够快的物体
for a massive enough or fast enough object.
考虑到希克苏鲁伯小行星
Considering that the Chicxulub asteroid
重如珠峰
weighed nearly as much as Mount Everest
速度超过时速5万英里
and was moving at over 50,000 miles an hour,
约是手枪子弹速度的50倍
about 50 times faster than a bullet from a revolver,
难怪它是宇宙间最大的爆炸之一
it's no wonder it was one of the biggest blasts in the universe.
但是它对整个地球结构的影响又当如何呢？
But what about its effect on the structure of the entire planet?
爆破专家把一小块炸药放在西瓜皮的下面
An explosives expert places a small charge just under the skin of a watermelon
来模拟这颗小行星撞上地球时能量释放的类型
to simulate the type of energy released when this asteroid slammed into Earth.
你可以看到 伤害我们的东西
As you can see, something that would be devastating to us
是不会太伤及整个地球的
is not too devastating to the planet as a whole,
所以还是有相当大的空间来对付更大的爆炸
So there's still plenty of room for the blasts to get bigger.
排名第9 - 火星撞击
幸运的是 火星而非地球成了一颗小行星的靶子
Luckily, Mars and not Earth was the target of an asteroid
它比撞上尤卡坦半岛的小行星大了200倍
200 times larger than the one that slammed into the Yucatan Peninsula.
39亿年前撞上火星的小行星有1200英里宽
The asteroid that impacted Mars about 3.9 billion years ago was 1,200 miles wide.
那大约是冥王星大小
Now, that's about the size of Pluto,
你不妨想象美国大陆的大部分
and if you imagine most of the continental U.S.,
从丹佛到佛罗里达的狭长地带
from Denver to the Florida panhandle
上至芝加哥 下至得克萨斯南部 庞大无比
and Chicago down to the south of Texas, huge.
那就是该小行星的大小
And that's just the size of the asteroid.
弹坑 叫做伯勒里斯盆地 是另外一个故事
The crater, known as the Borealis Basin, is another story.
坑洞覆盖了星球的40%
The hole covers about 40% of the planet.
火星伯勒里斯盆地宽约5300英里
So the Borealis Basin on Mars is about 5,300 miles wide.
我身后的弹坑只不过一英里宽
Now, the crater behind me is not even a mile wide,
所以你可以想象这个乘以5000倍
so you can imagine multiplying this by over 5,000 times,
那就是火星撞击坑的规模了
and that's the size of the impact crater on Mars.
那相当于非洲大陆的大小
That's about the size of the continent of Africa.
大得惊人
Amazingly huge.
虽然撞击火星的小行星的速度
While the speed of the asteroid that smacked Mars
与撞击尤卡坦半岛的那个大差不离
wasn't much different than the one that hit the Yucatan Peninsula,
但是质量要大上N多倍
the mass was many times greater,
导致了能量释放要大上好多
leading to a much larger release of energy.
能量或许大上100万倍
It's probably about a million times more energetic,
因此约是250兆兆吨的能量
so it'd be about 250 million million megatons of energy,
那是巨大的能量
and that's a lot of energy,
所以你会看到有这么大的一个盆地
and that's why you've got such a big, big basin.
今天要是那样的东西打击地球
Something like that hitting the Earth today
瞬间死亡的人数会达到数十亿之多
would put the instant death toll in the billions,
随后会抹去地球上所有的生命
and would probably wipe out all life on the planet soon after.
不过接下来的爆炸曾炸掉过我们星球更大的一块地壳
But the next blast did blow an even bigger chunk of crust off our planet,
所幸是在尚未面世之前
luckily, before life even existed here.
排名第8 - 大劈开
不是火星成了靶子
Instead of Mars being a target,
想象一下一颗大如火星的小行星撞上了地球
imagine an asteroid the size of Mars slamming into Earth.
多数行星科学家认为
Most planetary scientists believe
那就是地球在46亿年前
that's exactly what happened soon after the Earth
形成后不久所发生的事情
formed about 4.6 billion years ago.
它被称为大撞击学说
It's known as the Giant Impactor Theory,
也俗称大劈开
also nicknamed the Big Splat.
早期太阳系是个比今天热闹得多的地方
The early solar system was a much busier place than it is today.
基本上 它还未安顿下来
Basically, it hadn't settled down yet,
因此有大量的碎片在四处乱跑
so there are lots of fragments running around,
孳生了各种各样的碰撞
producing all sorts of collisions,
最终导致了我们今天所知的天体
which ultimately produced the bodies we know today.
地球当时还是熔岩一片 聊无生机
Earth was still a molten wasteland, devoid of life back then,
那是好事一桩 因为那次撞击的力道
which is a good thing, since the force of that collision
会让生命中途夭折
would have ended life in its tracks.
那么地球又是如何从史上最黄最暴力的
So how did the planet recover
事件中恢复过来的呢？
from the most violent event in its history?
宇宙间许多爆炸之最
Many of the biggest blasts in the universe
都是彗星和小行星撞上行星造成的
are caused by comets and asteroids slamming into planets.
这些撞击释放的能量可以是
These impacts can unleash hundreds of times more energy
地球整个核武器的数百倍还多
than the entire nuclear arsenal on Earth.
但是我们名录上的第8号甚至比那更强大
But number 8 on our list is even more powerful than that.
爆炸的肇因是一块大如行星的石头撞上了地球
A blast caused by a rock the size of a planet slamming into Earth.
它实际发生在地球形成后不久
It actually happened soon after the Earth had formed,
约46亿年前 当时一个大如火星的物体
about 4.6 billion years ago, when an object the size of Mars,
有时被称为忒伊亚
sometimes known as Theia,
撞上我们的星球 带来了灾难性的后果
slammed into our world with catastrophic effects.
相对撞上火星的冥王星大小的小行星
Compared to the Pluto-sized asteroid that smashed into Mars,
那块盯上地球的火星般大小的石头
the Mars-sized rock that nailed Earth
要大上三倍
was more than three times larger,
释放的动能更大
releasing much more kinetic energy.
敲掉地球外壳的忒伊亚撞击者
The Theia impactor that knocked off the crust of Earth
或许要比伯勒里斯盆地撞击者强大10倍
was probably about 10 times more powerful than the Borealis Basin impactor.
但是这个难以置信的破坏力
But this incredibly destructive force
也有一些很重要的好处
also had some very important benefits.
忒伊亚撞上地球
So when Theia impacted the Earth,
或许发生了一次侧击
it happened probably at a glancing blow,
这样一来 两颗行星的铁核
and in doing so, the iron cores of the two planets
实际上就融合在了一块 形成了更大的铁核 更大的地球
actually melded together and formed a larger iron core and a larger Earth.
现在忒伊亚的地幔可能在撞击中完全炸飞了
Now Theia's mantle probably got completely blown off
因为它比地球小一些
in this impact because it's a little smaller than Earth,
地球的部分地幔也炸飞了
and some of the Earth's mantle got blown off,
这样你就看到这种地幔碎片漂浮在四处 转动起来
so you have all this mantle debris floating around, orbiting,
它实际上兼并在一起形成了月球
and it actually coalesced to form the Moon.
月球稳定了地球的地轴
The Moon stabilized Earth's axis,
防止它倾斜失控
preventing it from tilting wildly,
从而保持了地球气候的稳定
which keeps Earth's climate steady.
它也将地球的自转速度减缓到我们目前的昼夜24小时
It also slowed Earth's rotation over time to the 24-hour days we have now.
再来模拟这个爆炸的威力
Once again, to simulate the power of this blast,
爆破专家在代表地球的西瓜上放上炸药
an explosives expert places a charge on a melon representing Earth.
这会把西瓜炸飞吗？
Could this be the one that blows the melon away?
尽管有很大的破坏
Even though there's a lot of damage,
基本结构还是完好无损
the basic structure is still intact.
由于撞击产生的高温
With the heat of the impact,
地球和碎片都熔化了
the Earth and the debris were both molten.
那种熔化状态就是
And that molten state is the reason
撞击没有留下巨大的撞击坑的原因所在
why the impact didn't leave a massive crater behind.
熔化的地球重新形成球状并最终冷却了
The molten Earth re-formed as a sphere and eventually cooled.
那么有无某种撞击可以将行星化为尘埃呢？
So is there any kind of impact that can turn a planet into dust?
排名第7 - 星球对撞
太空深处 两颗行星 -
Deep in space, two planets--
一颗大如金星 另一颗 大如地球 -
one the size of Venus, the other, Earth--
行将对撞
are on a collision course.
它们是石质行星 没准生存着生命
They're rocky planets, possibly even harboring life.
它们的太阳系里有东西
Something in their solar system
将它们拽出正常的轨道
has pulled them out of their regular orbits,
不是侧击
and instead of a glancing blow,
它们可是迎头相撞在一起
they smash together in a head-on collision.
那些行星上的任何一个人
Anyone standing on those planets
都将目睹到恐怖的事件
would have witnessed a terrifying event.
你可以设想一下 你直接看到
You can imagine, if you had a direct view
有行星直奔我们而来
of the planet moving toward us.
那意味着天空很快就会完全被
That means the sky would quickly fill completely
这颗行将撞上的行星所覆盖
with this planet about to impact,
于是它会那样在天上
and then it would be over like that.
它会迅速消灭生命
It would be such a rapid extinction of life
你或许就没时间去考虑
that you probably wouldn't have time to think about it.
那不是某些虚构的末日场景
This isn't some fictional doomsday scenario.
有些研究者认为这种大规模的爆炸
Some researchers think this massive blast
在过去的数百年里震撼过宇宙
rocked the cosmos within the last thousand years
发生在300光年外的一个双星系里
in a binary star system about 300 light-years away.
那就是白羊座里的BD + 20-307
It's known as BD + 20-307 in the constellation Aries.
它有大量的尘埃
It has a tremendous amount of dust in it,
尘埃量比我们太阳系多100万倍
a million times more dust than in our solar system.
我们认为这种尘埃的产生可能源自
We think that this dust may have been produced
两颗大如地球和金星的行星的撞击
by the collision of two planets roughly the size of the Earth and Venus,
迎面相撞
just head-on, whack!
各自粉身碎骨 产生出大量的尘埃
Shattering each other, producing a tremendous amount of dust.
需要大量的能量
It takes enormous amounts of energy
将两颗行星都粉碎至尘埃
for two planets to pulverize each other into dust.
现在已不是地球核武器的数百倍了
Now instead of hundreds of times the world's nuclear arsenal,
我们讨论的是那个能量的数百万倍乃至数十亿倍了
we're talking millions of times or even billions of times that energy.
用上更大的炸药了
With this even larger charge,
我们不只是要炸掉这西瓜的一块
we're not just going to break off a chunk of this melon.
我们要将它炸得粉身碎骨
We're going to blow it to smithereens.
尽管行星碰撞可以是恐怖和毁灭性的
But as terrifying and destructive as planetary collisions can be,
但是它们还是远远小于恒星所产生的各种爆炸
they're still much smaller than the different types of blasts that come from stars.
那是不可同日而语的
It's a whole new ballgame.
其主要原因就在于恒星的质量远大于
The main reason is that there's a lot more mass in a star
任何一颗行星规模的天体
than any planet-sized object,
于是 存在着各种机制
and then, there are all kinds of mechanisms
可以发生在核聚变中
that can take place involving nuclear fusion,
引力塌缩的各个过程中
various processes that involve gravitational collapse,
也可以产生出大量的能量
which can derive a lot of energy as well.
这些高能爆炸之一就是我们名录上的第6号
One of these energetic blasts is number 6 on our list.
排名第6 - 磁星爆发
磁星是快速旋转的中子星
Magnetars are rapidly spinning neutron stars,
其形成是比我们太阳大数倍的恒星
which form when stars several times larger than our Sun
垂死并自我垮塌
begin to die and collapse in upon themselves.
想象一下 如果我们的86 5万英里宽的太阳
Imagine if our 865,000-mile-wide Sun
突然被压缩成12英里长的
suddenly compacted to the 12-mile length
曼哈顿岛
of the island of Manhattan.
所有的物质都被压缩成非常致密的东西
All of that matter is condensed into something so dense,
估计比钢铁要坚固100百亿倍
it's estimated to be 10 billion times stronger than steel.
为了让你有概念 中子星材料有多致密
To give you an idea of how incredibly dense neutron star material is,
如果这盖子里装的是中子星材料
if this cap was filled with neutron star stuff,
它在地球上会重达1000亿吨
it would weigh 100 billion tons on Earth,
远超过此山 差不多是整个山脉
more than this hill, as much as an entire mountain.
磁星名字的由来是基于这样一个事实
The magnetar name comes from the fact
某些中子星 其原因尚且不明
that certain neutron stars, for reasons that are still unknown,
具有宇宙间最强的磁场
have the strongest magnetic fields in the universe.
磁星的磁场异常强烈
The magnetic field of a magnetar is exceptionally strong.
它可以是地球磁场的1000兆倍
It can be 1,000 trillion times as strong as Earth's magnetic field.
真是了不得
That's fantastic.
磁场之强烈
The magnetic fields are so intense
要是有一颗磁星突然出现在
that if a magnetar suddenly appeared
地球与月球之间
halfway between the Earth and the Moon,
会强烈到足以
it would be strong enough
破坏地球上所有的电子设备
to disrupt all of the electronic equipment on the planet,
包括抹去地球上所有信用卡上的信息
including stripping the information off every credit card on Earth.
磁星爆发异常强劲的原因
And the reason magnetar flares are so powerful
就在于磁星特定区域周围的磁场
is that the magnetic fields around certain areas of the star
有时会自我扭曲得非常厉害
sometimes twist themselves so much
直到它们无法再进一步扭曲了 然后突然像弹簧那样松开了
that they can't twist any more, and suddenly release like a spring.
过程类似于太阳耀斑
The process is similar to a solar flare
因为就是磁场源源不断把能量输送上来
in that it's the magnetic field that's giving rise to the energy.
正是磁力线在各个方向不停地摆动
It's the shaking and tangling and sometimes the reconnection
纠缠 有时是重新连接
of lines of force going in different directions
输送能量驱动了爆发
that gives the energy that powers the flare.
然而不同于行星碰撞的动能作为主导
But unlike planetary collisions, where kinetic energy dominates,
磁星爆发发射的大部分能量
magnetar flares shoot out most of their energy
是电磁辐射
as electromagnetic radiation,
换句话说 就是光
in other words, light.
尤其是磁星爆发
And one magnetar flare in particular
强大到足以在5万光年外让绕地卫星失聪
was strong enough to blind satellites orbiting Earth from 50,000 light-years away.
宇宙的爆炸之最
The biggest blasts in the universe
是我们在地球上能想象的东西所无法比拟的
dwarf anything we can imagine on Earth.
它们已数十亿倍地超越了
They're already billions of times beyond
世界上全部的核武器
the entire nuclear arsenal of the world.
我们的倒数第6是耀斑爆发
Number 6 on our countdown are the flares that burst
来自极端磁化的中子星 叫做磁星
from incredibly magnetized neutron stars, known as magnetars.
地球史上观察到最强烈的一个
And one of the most powerful ever observed from Earth
在短短的1/10秒里释放的能量
released as much energy in just over a tenth of a second
相当于我们太阳1万年里释放的总和
as our Sun does in about 100,000 years.
2004年里的爆发来自一颗磁星
The blast in 2004 came from a magnetar
叫做SGR 1806-20 在在人马座里
known as SGR 1806-20, in the constellation Sagittarius.
它距离地球约5万光年
It's about 50,000 light-years away from Earth
在银河系的另一头
on the far side of the Milky Way.
它的强劲令人难以置信
It was incredibly powerful.
所有能量出自1/10秒里
All that energy came in a tenth of a second.
它冲击了刚好飞经上空的卫星探测器
It blasted the detectors in satellites that happened to be flying around up there.
事实上 它是史上所见到的最亮的
In fact, it was the brightest blast ever seen
我们太阳系外的天体爆炸
from an object outside our solar system.
可是它远在5万光年之外
And yet it was 50,000 light-years away.
然而亮度与爆炸的威力必定有关联吗？
But what does brightness have to do with the power of a blast?
我现在是在一间黑暗的房间里
So I'm standing in a dark room here,
现在我把灯打开
and now I'm going to turn on a light bulb.
呈现给我的灯光亮度取决于两个要素
How bright that light bulb appears to me depends on two factors.
它本质上取决于灯泡有多强或多亮 - 它的功率
It depends on how intrinsically powerful or luminous the light bulb is--its wattage,
它每秒钟发出多少能量
how much energy it puts out per second.
同时也取决于灯泡与我的距离
And it also depends on the distance of the light bulb from me.
我靠近灯泡 就会看到灯泡是明亮的
When I'm close to the light bulb, I see that the light bulb is bright.
如果我的距离增加一倍
If I move a factor of two farther away,
那么事实上 它看上去就会减弱四倍
then, in fact, it looks a factor of four fainter.
那就是光的平方反比定律
That's the inverse square law of light.
灯泡的功率始终保持不变
The power of the light bulb has remained the same.
但是在一倍远的距离上
But by being twice as far away,
我就只得到1/4的光线射到我的脸 我的眼睛
I get only 1/4 of the light reaching my face and my eyes.
天文学家测量了恒星或爆发的表现亮度
Astronomers measure the apparent brightness of the star or the explosion.
他们通过其它手段计算出它的距离
They figure out its distance through some other technique.
根据这两个变量
And from those two variables,
他们计算出了光源的功率或亮度
they figure out the power or the luminosity of the source.
所释放出来的光 不只是可见光波长
That light is released, not just in visible wavelengths,
而是整个电磁波谱
but across the electromagnetic spectrum.
研究人员随时都在侦查伽玛射线
And any time researchers detect gamma rays,
就像他们对磁星爆发所做的那样知道它必定是个大爆炸
like they do in magnetar flares, they know it must be a big blast.
伽玛射线是光的一种
Gamma rays are a type of light,
但是要比我们肉眼所见的光强劲N多倍
but a much more energetic light than we see with our eyes.
我们熟悉的光谱 从很低的能量开始
So the spectrum of light that we're familiar with goes from very low energy
经过频谱的可见部分
and through the visible part of the spectrum,
我们见到的光 一直到X射线
the light that we see, all the way out through x-rays
进入了这个光的极高能部分
into this extremely high-energy component of light,
那叫做伽玛射线
which is called gamma rays.
即使是1/10秒的短暂伽玛射线爆发 比如SGR 1806-20
Even a 1/10-of-a-second short gamma ray flare, like SGR 1806-20,
依然能够在许多光年外用辐射来煎熬地球
would still be able to fry the Earth with radiation from many light-years away,
只要爆发的全部力道对准地球的话
as long as the full force of the flare was aimed at Earth.
不过宇宙中并非所有的爆炸之最
But not all of the biggest blasts in the universe
都是瞬间完成的
are over in a fraction of a second.
排名第6 - 亿年爆炸
距离地球26亿光年处 一个超大质量黑洞
2.6 billion light-years away from Earth, a supermassive black hole,
我们太阳质量的数十亿倍
billions of times the mass of our Sun,
一直横行霸道在一个星系团的中央
has been wreaking havoc in the center of a cluster of galaxies.
叫做MSA 735
Known as MSA 735,
它一刻不停地喷射着两束粒子流
it's been shooting out two continuous jets of particles
朝着对应的两个方向
in opposite directions.
科学家认喷射已经肆虐了上亿年了
Scientists believe the jets have been raging for the past hundred million years,
在周围的星系里冲出两个巨大的泡沫
punching two huge bubbles into the surrounding galaxies.
MSA 735 确实是黑洞吹泡泡的原型样本
MSA 735 really is the prototypical example of a black hole blowing bubbles.
我们所看到的就是正被这些强大的
What we're seeing here is giant cavities
射流掏空的巨大的空洞
being evacuated by these powerful jets.
它们把大量的能量从黑洞里
They transport vast sums of energy
传送到极远处
down from the black hole out to huge distances,
或许有百万光年之远
maybe about a million light-years or so.
百万光年是我们银河系宽度的10倍
A million light-years is 10 times wider than our Milky Way Galaxy,
那意味着这些喷射强大到足以
which means these jets are powerful enough
产生两个非常大的泡沫
to create two very big bubbles.
这两个泡沫的总能量大的惊人
The total energy within these two bubbles is stupendous,
远超过我们在宇宙间所知的
far exceeding any other amount of concentrated energy
任何一种集束能量
that we know of in the universe.
不管怎样 务必记住
However, it must be remembered
能量的释放已超过了100万年
that the energy was released over 100 million years.
那意味着每个单位时间里
That means that per unit of time
所释放的总能量并不都是这么大的
the total amount of energy released wasn't all that big.
然而 喷射还是强大到足以
Still, the jets are strong enough
以时速数百万英里把粒子射出
to shoot the particles out at millions of miles an hour,
约为光速的四分之一
about a quarter of the speed of light.
喷射并产生泡沫
The jets and resulting bubbles
只出自宇宙中最庞大的黑洞的1%
only come from about 1% of the most massive black holes in the universe.
那是因为这些怪物附近的力道非常大
That's because the forces near these monsters are so huge
不是在吞噬一切
that instead of swallowing everything,
而是它们实际上最终在将一些粒子推得远远的
they actually end up pushing some particles away.
需要强调的是 这些巨大的爆发
It's important to emphasize that these giant explosions
并非黑洞本身的爆发
are not the explosion of the black hole itself,
而是粒子喷射
but rather an ejection of particles
来自附近的黑洞 周边的黑洞
from near the black hole, the vicinity of the black hole.
通过彼此碰撞
By colliding with one another,
在某种情况下 它们可以被射出
they can, in some cases, be ejected out of the vicinity
邻近的黑洞
of the black hole.
然而如何才能让这种两面的爆发
But how can this two-sided blast
有可能持续上亿年的呢？
possibly keep going for 100 million years?
关键在于有多少宇宙材料可供利用
It's all a matter of how much cosmic stuff is available
如行星 恒星被拉伸撕裂
as planets and suns are stretched and ripped apart
至原子本身 并拽入黑洞
down to their very atoms and drawn towards the black hole.
因此这些喷射 我们估计已持续了
So these jets that we've estimated have been going on
约1亿年了
for about 100 million years
依然还有大量的燃料可供它们利用
still have a huge amount of fuel available to them.
那个过程可以继续很长的时间
That process can go on for an extremely long time,
数亿年之久
hundreds of millions of years.
现在来想象一下 让大量的能量
Now imagine taking a big chunk of that energy
在两秒不到的时间释放出来
and releasing it in less than two seconds.
那就是研究人员认为在排名第4的爆炸中所发生的情景
That's what researchers believe happens in blast number 4.
排名第4 - 短伽玛射线暴
伽玛射线暴比磁星爆发更为集束
Gamma ray bursts are more concentrated than magnetar flares.
它是辐射集束 宛如激光束
It's a concentrated beam of radiation, like a laser beam.
它的出现就像是狭窄的射流
It comes out as a narrow stream.
集束的伽玛射线的速度也远快于
The gamma rays in the beams are also traveling much faster
黑洞喷射出的粒子流
than the particles coming out of black hole jets.
观察表明 能量表现在射流里
The observations show that the energy is coming out in jets,
速度接近光速
moving at very close to the speed of light,
达到了光速的99 9999%
99.9999% the speed of light.
以那个匪夷所思的速度就在短短的十分之几秒时间里
At that mind-bending speed, in just a few tenths of a second,
短伽玛射线暴能够释放出的能量
short gamma ray bursts can release as much energy
相当于我们太阳数百万年里的释放量
as our Sun does in millions of years.
但是多年来 科学家没能搞明白
But for years scientists couldn't figure out
为何有些伽玛射线暴是长的
why some gamma ray bursts were long,
持续许多秒甚至几分钟
lasting many seconds or even minutes,
而其他的则通常只有若干分之一秒钟
while others were usually only a fraction of a second.
2005年的一个爆发
Then one burst in 2005
让研究人员有了一个令人兴奋的新理论
led researchers to an exciting new theory
关于极其致密的中子星的相互湮灭
about incredibly dense neutron stars annihilating each other.
人造原子弹的威力相比宇宙间
The power of manmade atomic bombs is nothing
惊天动地的星系爆发来说 简直可以忽略不计了
compared to the galaxy-rattling explosions in the cosmos.
随着我们继续倒数
As we continue counting down
宇宙中的10大爆炸
10 of the biggest blasts in the universe,
这些灾难性的事件现在产生的能量
these cataclysmic events are now producing as much energy
都动辄就是我们太阳数以百万年计的量
as our Sun does in millions of years.
短伽玛射线暴为第4号
Short gamma ray bursts are number 4.
多年来 科学家一直对
For years, scientists have been confident
长伽玛射线暴的源头了如指掌
of the source of long gamma ray bursts,
就是那些持续两秒钟以上
those that last over two seconds
甚至爆发许多分钟的
and sometimes erupt for many minutes.
它们都是来自有大质量恒星的星系
They come from galaxies with massive stars.
某些大质量恒星死亡时 会塌缩爆发
And when certain massive stars die, they collapse and then explode,
以集束伽玛射线喷射出巨量的能量
blasting out incredible amounts of energy as concentrated jets of gamma rays.
但是在2005年 太空探测器捕捉到的强烈的伽玛射线暴
But in 2005, detectors in space captured a powerful gamma ray burst
只持续了一秒钟还不到
that only lasted for a fraction of a second.
那令人非常激动
This was very exciting,
因为我们以前所见到的伽玛射线暴
because all the gamma ray bursts we'd seen before
是完全不同的类型 -
were of the different variety--
时间较长 出自有大量恒星在垂死挣扎的星系
longer, coming from galaxies where massive stars were dying.
这个是不同的东西
This was something different.
它历时短暂 它所产生的区域里
It was short, and it came from a region
没有大质量恒星的存在
where no massive stars existed.
这个爆炸所产生的星系被认为存在着
This burst came from a galaxy thought to have
一些极其致密的中子星 成双结对
some incredibly dense neutron stars in binary pairs
相互缠绕
that orbit each other.
科学家认为产生如此快速
And scientists believe that the only way
和强劲的伽玛射线暴的唯一途径
to generate such a quick and powerful burst of gamma rays
就是一旦两颗中子星卷入了致命的舞蹈
is if two neutron stars engage in a deadly dance,
相互围绕越来越亲近 最终会彼此撞在一起
orbiting closer and closer, then finally crashing into each other.
此时被认为是黑洞诞生的一刻
This is thought to be the moment when a black hole is born.
两颗中子星最终碰头时
When the two neutron stars finally touch,
其中的一颗中子星会被撕碎变成圆环
one of the neutron stars gets shredded into a disc
剩余的部分已不足以成为中子星了
and the thing that's left is too big to be a neutron star.
宇宙间已没有什么力量能够容纳两颗中子星
There's no force in the universe that can hold up two neutron stars,
因此它就塌缩成了黑洞
so it collapses to a black hole.
2005年的事件 即所谓的GRB 050509b
The 2005 event, known as GRB 050509b,
因为第二次爆发发生在
since it was the second burst to occur
那年的5月9日
on May 9th of that year,
首个短伽玛射线暴就被定位了
was the first short gamma ray burst whose location was pinned down.
在地球看来 它并不十分明亮
It didn't look very bright from Earth,
但那是因为它是在惊人的22亿光年之外
but that's because it was an astounding 2.2 billion light-years away.
GRB 0509b只持续了约40毫秒
GRB 0509b lasted only about 40 milliseconds.
然而就在那段时间里 它所释放的能量
But in that time, it released about as much energy
达到了太阳在一亿年里的释放量
as the Sun will release in a hundred million years.
但是恒星碰撞的力量
But the power of colliding stars
是无法与整个恒星从内部爆发所产生的
can't compete with the even larger amount of energy released
更大的量同日而语的
when an entire star explodes from the inside out.
大恒星死亡时
When large stars die,
它们并不会就像我们的太阳那样黯然退场
they don't just fizzle out like our Sun eventually will.
它们会在爆发中辞世
They go out with a bang.
它们其实有几种类型
There are actually several types,
不过超新星爆发的两种主要方式
but the two main ways a supernova explosion happens
要么是双星系里的一颗恒星
is either when one star in a binary star system
吞噬掉其伙伴的部分或全部
swallows part or all of its companion,
要么是超大质量恒星自身垮塌
or when a supermassive star collapses in on itself
在那个过程中将其外壳喷射出去
and ejects its outer shell in the process.
无论哪种方式 难以想象的能量被迅速释放出来
Either way, a mind-boggling amount of energy is quickly released.
动能 喷射物质的动能
The energy of motion, the kinetic energy of the ejected material
可以相当于太阳在整个100亿年的生命周期里
can equal the total amount of energy
所释放的能量总和
that the Sun will release over its entire 10-billion-year lifetime.
双星型的超新星类似于氢弹
The binary star type of supernova is similar to a hydrogen bomb,
一旦核聚变失控就会导致大爆发
where runaway nuclear fusion leads to a massive explosion.
这些被称为1a型超新星
These are known as Type 1a Supernovas,
在2003年 其中的一个爆发涌进宇宙的光线
and in 2003, one of these blasts flooded the cosmos with more light
超过了众多恒星组成的整个星系
than an entire galaxy of stars combined.
它比太阳亮出了200亿倍
It was over 20 billion times more luminous than the Sun
持续了约两个星期
for about two weeks.
这一切都来自某些物体的爆发
And this all came from the explosion
它并不比月球大多少
of something not much bigger than the Moon,
质量约是太阳1 4倍
about 1.4 times the mass of the Sun,
是一次热核爆炸 是核聚变
from a thermonuclear explosion, from fusion.
对于核塌缩型超新星来说
For the core-collapse type of supernova,
难以置信的能量产生在于
an incredible amount of power is generated
其外壳收缩
when the outer shell slams down
受到了致密星核巨大的反冲力
and gets an extra kick from the denser core of the star.
试想这个乒乓球作为恒星外面的较轻的材料
Imagine this ping-pong ball represents that outer, lighter material of the star,
而这个超级球作为较重的内核
whereas this super ball represents the heavy inner core.
你可以看到乒乓球
You can see that the ping-pong ball
实际上靠自身并不会弹跳很多
actually doesn't really bounce that much on its own,
这是超级球的弹跳
and there's the bounce of the super ball.
然而你将看到的是 我把它们一起落下
But what you'll see is that when I send them down together,
超级球的反弹
the bounce of the super ball back up
会把乒乓球推得很高
will propel the ping-pong ball much higher.
那非常像超新星里的情况
And that's very much like what happens in the supernova,
那里 你有较重的内核向外反弹
where you have the heavy inner core bouncing back out
遇上较轻的物质 将其炸出来
and meeting that lighter material and blowing it out.
事实上 2005年的一颗超新星爆发 即SN 2005ap
In fact, one supernova explosion in 2005, known as SN 2005ap,
数周内一直就比其他恒星更加闪亮
flashed brighter than all of the others for weeks on end.
不过它并没有给地球带来任何伤害
But it didn't do any damage to Earth
因为 庆幸的是 它也是在47亿光年之外
because, luckily, it was also 4.7 billion light-years away.
和头10位的其它排名一样
And like many of the other blasts on the top 10 list,
超新星并不只是破坏
supernovas don't just destroy.
超新星有点像回收中心
A supernova is a little bit like a recycling center.
这些超大质量恒星有大量的材料
There's a lot of material in those massive stars.
其质量是我们太阳的8倍到100多倍不等
It's anything from eight times to over a hundred times the mass of our Sun.
因此有大量的材料
So there's a lot of material
会在那些恒星中得到处理
that's going to be processed in those stars,
宛如有大量的材料在回收中心这里
just like there's a lot of raw material here at the recycling center
进行处理一般
that's going to be processed.
宇宙中的元素以轻元素为主
The matter in the universe is dominated by light elements,
如氢和氦
like hydrogen and helium,
但是即将成为超新星的恒星内部
but the inside of a star about to go supernova
是伴随我们终身的各种金属
is the main source of the various metals
及其它重元素的主要来源
and other heavy elements we depend on for life.
就像这些材料被分类成不同的类别
Just like these materials are being sorted into different categories,
恒星也在着手处理着越来越重的元素
the star starts to process heavier and heavier elements,
开始是氢 接着是氦
starting with hydrogen, then helium,
制造着越来越重的元素 一直到铁
making heavier and heavier elements all the way up to iron,
此时聚变过程终告结束
when the fusion process stops.
在其成为超新星后 继续着它的生命
Later on in its life when it becomes supernova,
借助于超新星的挤压效应
with the aid of the compression effect in the supernova,
恒星会制造出更加重的元素
the star will make even heavier elements.
就像这些材料被打包处理
Just as these materials are now packaged and processed
准备离开回收中心
and ready to leave the recycling center
出去重新使用一样
and go out into the world to be reused,
产自恒星的材料
the materials that were made in the stars
最终会被经过超新星的加工调制
that were then finally cooked and blown out into the universe
炸入宇宙中
by the supernova process,
也将被重新使用
those will be reused as well.
它们可能被其他恒星甚至其他行星利用
They may be used in other stars or perhaps other planets.
构成我们地球的材料
The materials that we're made of here on Earth,
甚至我们身体的材料
the materials even in our bodies,
那些重元素都是超新星制造的
those heavy elements were made in supernovae.
虽然超新星本身就是巨大的爆发
While supernovas are massive explosions themselves,
但是它们还能用更为集中的能量触发二次爆炸
they can also trigger secondary blasts with even more concentrated energy.
长伽玛射线暴
The long gamma ray burst
出自最强烈的超新星爆发
comes out of the most powerful supernova explosions.
它们强如短伽玛射线暴
They're as strong as the short gamma ray bursts,
但是由于它们持续时间更长
but since they last much longer,
会从2秒到近半小时不等
anywhere from two seconds to nearly half an hour,
它们总体上爆发出更多的能量
they blast out much more energy overall.
长伽玛射线暴相对短伽玛射线暴
The long gamma ray bursts are completely different beasts
是完全不同的巨兽
compared to the short gamma ray bursts.
它们更加强烈无比
They're immensely more powerful,
或许会比短期爆发强烈1万倍
maybe up to around 10,000 times more powerful than the short-duration bursts.
这些超新星爆发所产生的集束能量
These concentrated jets of energy only come from supernova explosions
只涉及那些质量是我们太阳的30倍乃至更多的恒星
involving stars 30 or more times the mass of our Sun.
就像短伽玛射线暴那样
And just like the short gamma ray bursts,
它们是黑洞诞生的证据
they're evidence of the birth of a black hole.
长伽玛射线暴在某种意义上是
Long gamma ray bursts are, in some sense,
一种超能超新星
a variety of hyper-energetic supernova.
铁核塌缩 如前所述 会成为中子星
The iron core collapses, as before, to a neutron star,
但有太多的材料塌缩进去的话
but too much material falls down on it,
它是不能停留在中子星上的
and it can't stay a neutron star.
温度会升至100亿度
The temperature rises to 10 billion degrees.
其一立方英寸的亮度会大如太阳
The luminosity in one cubic inch of this is as big as the Sun,
这种能量是无法从赤道上流出的
and this power can't flow out on the equator.
它经过了聚焦 就像是猎枪发射一样
It gets focused, like in a shotgun blast,
从恒星的旋转轴射出
out the rotational axis of the star.
最强烈的长伽玛射线暴相对我们的太阳
So how much energy do the most powerful long gamma ray bursts release
会释放出多少能量呢？
compared to our Sun?
答案是惊人的
The answer is shocking.
我们来到了宇宙间爆炸之最的排名第2 - 长伽玛射线暴
We're at number 2 in our countdown of the biggest blasts in the universe:
它们是宇宙中最强大的集束能
They're the most powerful concentrated beams of energy in the universe.
它们在几秒乃至几分钟里所释放出的能量
They release many times more energy in a matter of seconds or minutes
无数倍于我们太阳在其整个100亿年的寿命里所产生的能量
than our Sun will produce in its entire 10-billion-year life span.
它们毁灭性威力的关键
The key to their devastating power
就在于将能量聚焦于一个狭窄的区域里
is focusing that energy in a narrow area.
枪械专家用两支不同的猎枪来说明这一点
A firearms expert illustrates the point with two different shotguns.
首先 短筒枪 弹丸很快飞出枪管
First, a shorter gun, where the shot spreads out quickly
并不像伽玛射线暴
after leaving the barrel, unlike a gamma ray burst.
你可以看到 对西瓜有一些伤害
As you can see, there's some damage to the melon,
但是并不厉害 因为弹丸散开了
but not that much, because the shot was spread out
只有一些击中目标
and only some of it hit the target.
现在我们的枪械专家换上长筒枪
Now our firearms expert is switching to a longer barrel
能让弹丸在抵达靶子过程中 保持紧凑模式 -
that keeps the shot concentrated in a tighter pattern as it goes downrange--
效果如同伽玛射线暴那样
the same effect as a gamma ray burst.
集束弹丸可以是毁灭性的
Concentrating the shot can be devastating.
我们庆幸的是 大多数伽玛射线暴
It's a good thing for us that most gamma ray bursts
都距离地球数百万乃至数十亿光年之远
are millions or billions of light-years away from Earth
并且指向别的方向
and are pointed in the other direction.
据信那些集束射流
It's believed that these concentrated jets
是大质量恒星塌缩成黑洞时发出的
shoot out when massive stars collapse into black holes.
2008年 科学家发现了
And in 2008, scientists detected
有记录的最强大的伽玛射线暴之一
one of the strongest gamma ray bursts on record,
叫做GRB 080916c
known as GRB 080916c.
它持续了难以置信的23分钟
It lasted an incredible 23 minutes.
这个伽玛射线暴是迄今所见过的最令人兴奋的爆发之一
This GRB was one of the most exciting blasts ever seen,
因为从观察亮度及爆发的距离推断其总能量
because the total power inferred from the observed brightness
超过了那时之前所有的伽玛射线暴
and the distance of the blast exceeded that of any other known GRB up to that time.
此外 我们可以看出高能粒子
Moreover, we can tell that energetic particles
沿着两个射流轰出 速度达到了光速的99 9999%
were blasted out along two jets at 99.9999% of the speed of light.
伽玛射线暴异常强烈 粒子和辐射束
GRBs are so powerful along the beam of particles and radiation
哪怕是在数千光年外
that even ones that are thousands of light-years away,
但要是指向我们 就会摧毁地球上的大部分生命
but pointing at us, could destroy much of the life on Earth.
但是如果说长伽玛射线暴
But if long gamma ray bursts
是宇宙中最强烈的爆炸的话
are the most powerful explosions in the universe,
那么它们怎么能够屈居我们名录的第二号呢？
then how could they be number 2 on our list?
因为位列榜首的东西
Because the top spot goes to something
并没有发生在宇宙里面
that didn't happen within the universe,
而是发生在宇宙本身诞生时
but happened when the universe itself was formed.
排名第1 - 大爆炸
所有爆炸之母
This mother of all blasts
严格地说是膨胀而非爆发
is technically an expansion and not an explosion,
因为它不是特定区域里的爆炸
since it was not a blast within a defined area.
它不是发生在太空某个地方的爆发
It wasn't an explosion that happened somewhere in space.
那是整个空间
It's all of space.
它是时空结构本身的从无到有
It's the actual fabric of space-time itself coming into existence.
因此在爆炸之最的概念中 称其为大理所当然
So in the concept of a biggest blast, it's as big as it gets.
整个宇宙在爆炸中诞生
It was the whole universe blasting into existence.
大爆炸的速度和温度
And the speed and temperatures of the Big Bang
让宇宙诞生后其中所发生的一切都相形见绌了
dwarf anything that happened inside the universe once it was formed.
那些温度超乎我们的想象
Those temperatures are beyond anything we can imagine.
如果你用常量去衡量 它们是以万亿度计的
They're trillions of degrees if you measured it in the usual units,
因此相对任何爆炸
so compared to any explosions,
可以说 在地球上 恒星上 或者你说吧
say, here on Earth or a star or what have you,
都是远远够不上的
this is well beyond that.
研究人员认为 理论上 他们可以回到
Researchers believe that, theoretically, they can go back
非常接近大爆炸发生的那一刻
so close to the moment the Big Bang happened,
就是那个不能再往前的那个瞬间
that a fraction of a second doesn't come anywhere close
去做时间的裁判
to doing the time scale justice.
大爆炸之暴
The bang of the Big Bang
是早期宇宙所谓的大膨胀的时刻
is a time in the early universe known as Inflation.
宇宙飞快扩大
The size of the universe went whoosh.
膨胀之快 扩大无数倍
It just expanded so quickly, doubled in size many times
就在弹指一挥间
over a very, very short interval of time.
这种惊人的膨胀 指数般的爆扩态势
This incredible inflationary, exponential state of expansion
只持续了瞬间
lasted only a tiny fraction of a second,
百万分之   百万分之
a millionth of a millionth of a millionth of a millionth
百万分之   百万分之一秒钟
of a millionth of a millionth of a second.
在这种早期膨胀中
During this early expansion,
似乎一切都速度快过
it seemed as if things were moving faster
爱因斯坦的宇宙速度极限 - 光速
than Einstein's universal speed limit, the speed of light.
事实上 膨胀之快
In fact, it expanded so quickly
快过了光速
that it was faster than the speed of light.
没关系
That's okay.
那并不违背爱因斯坦的相对论
That doesn't violate Einstein's Theory of Relativity.
空间本身的膨胀可以快过光速
Space itself can expand faster than the speed of light.
没有粒子可以在空间穿行快过光速
No particle can travel through space faster than the speed of light,
但是空间本身可以也确实膨胀快过了光速
but space itself can and does expand faster than the speed of light.
大爆炸是最值得纪念的
And the Big Bang is the largest reminder of all
在宇宙间所有爆炸之最中
that the biggest blasts in the universe,
在那些能量的突然释放之中
these sudden releases of energy,
其作用远超过毁灭
do much more than destroy.
我们宇宙的诞生
The creation of our universe,
群星璀璨的诞生
the creation of the sunshine that comes out of stars
我们月亮的诞生
and the creation of our own Moon,
通通来自这个能量的突然解放
all came from this tremendous liberation of energy all at once.
紧密的联系就在于物质一方面出现
So there's a very intimate link between matter manifested in one way
然后消亡
and then being destroyed
然后以新的方式重新出现
and then re-emerging in a new way,
以及 你知道就在地球上它重新出现成为了我们
and, you know, here on Earth, it re-emerged as us.
随着宇宙的演化 其最大的爆炸
And as the universe evolves, its biggest blasts
将继续扮演世界的毁灭者以及新机会的创造者
will continue to be both the destroyer of worlds